# Lorenzo Fabbri

## Summary

I am a PhD student at the Barcelona Institute for Global Health (ISGlobal). I work under the supervision of Prof. Martine Vrijheid. My main topic of interest is the use of modern Causal Inference methods to answer questions in the broad field of Environmental Neuroepidemiology. I am also profoundly interested in Open Science and Reproducible Research.

I received my Bachelor's degree in Biotechnology and my Master's degree in Quantitative and Computational Biology. My personal webpage can be found here. You can also find me on Bluesky and GitHub.

## Working Experience

PhD Student Barcelona Institute for Global Health (Barcelona, ES)	2021 - Present
Student Research Assistant Fellowship	
Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2017 - 2017
Research Visits	
Visiting PhD Student	
Harvard Pilgrim Health Care (Boston, US)	2024 - 2024
Funding	
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures	
Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2024
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures	
ATHLETE (Barcelona, ES)	2024
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures	
Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red (Madrid, ES)	2024
Meritatamente 2022	
Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2022
Erasmus+ Traineeship Programme Scholarship	
University of Trento (Trento, IT)	2019
Faculty of Informatics Scholarship	
Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2016
Erasmus Traineeship Programme Scholarship	
University of Parma (Parma, IT)	2015
TT 1 4 1	
Honors and Awards	
Outstanding Abstract by a Student International Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022
invernational Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022
Publications	

My ORCiD is 0000-0003-3031-322X.

- 1. **Fabbri L**, Garlantézec R, Audouze K, et al. Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: A panel study. *Environment International*. Published online February 26, 2023:107856. doi:10.1016/j.envint.2023.107856
- 2. Thiel C, Cordes H, **Fabbri L**, et al. A Comparative Analysis of Drug-Induced Hepatotoxicity in Clinically Relevant Situations. *PLOS Computational Biology*. 2017;13(2):e1005280. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005280

#### Conference Presentations

The posters can be found here.

# Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: a panel study

ISEE Annual Conference, Athens (GR)

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

2022

2022

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

International Prenatal Programing and Toxicity Meeting (online)

2022

Efficient and Portable MPI Support for Approximate Bayesian Computation

Platform for Advanced Scientific Computing Conference, Lugano (CH)

2017

#### Education

#### PhD Programme in Biomedicine

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (Barcelona, ES)

EURION Cluster Annual Meeting (online)

2021 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Martine Vrijheid.

#### M.Sc. in Quantitative and Computational Biology

Università degli Studi di Trento (Trento, IT)

2017 - 2019

- Thesis (FBK, Trento (IT)): Machine Learning for Predictive Drug Induced Hepatotoxicity. Supervised by: Dr. Cesare Furlanello, Dr. Marco Chierici, Prof. Enrico Domenici.
- Internship (HITS, Heidelberg (DE)): Machine and Deep Learning for Predictive Unbinding Kinetics of Kinases. Supervised by: Prof. Rebecca Wade, Dr. Daria Kokh, Prof. Raffaello Potestio.
- Final mark: 110/110 With Honors.

#### M.Sc. Student in Computational Science

Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)

2016 - 2017

- Project (USI, Lugano (CH)): Investigation by Computational Techniques of Channelopaties related to Sodium Channels. Supervised by: Prof. Vittorio Limongelli, Prof. Daniele Di Marino.

#### B.Sc. in Biotechnology

University of Parma (Parma, IT)

2012 - 2016

- Thesis (RWTH, Aachen (DE)): Whole Body PBPK Modeling of Valproic Acid. Supervised by: Prof. Elena Maestri, Prof. Lars M. Blank, Dr. Henrik Cordes.
- Final mark: 103/110.

## Continuing Education

#### Spring School in Causal Inference with Observational Data

Causal Insights, Leeds (UK)

Apr 2022

## Computational Bayesian methods using brms in R

Physalia Courses, online Feb 2022

## **ELIXIR Omics Integration and Systems Biology**

National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden, online Sep 2021

#### Fundamentals of Epidemiology (EPM101)

LSHTM, online Sep 2021

#### Advanced Statistics: Statistical Modelling

Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, online Aug 2021

### Alpine Exposome Summer School

Inserm and ATHLETE, online Jun 2021

## Metabolomics Data Processing and Data Analysis

University of Birmingham, online Feb 2021

Mendelian Randomisation	
Imperial College London, online	May 2020
Image Analysis and Modeling of Complex Biological Dynamics University of Wurzburg, Wurzburg (DE)	Sep 2017
Effective High Performance Computing Summer School CSCS and University of Lugano, Lugano (CH)	Jul 2017
MARVEL School on Variationally Enhanced Sampling University of Lugano, Lugano (CH)	Feb 2017
Advanced Course in Alternatives to Animal Experimentation University of Genova, Genoa (IT)	Nov 2015
Service	
Students and New Researchers Network International Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022 - 2023
Early Career Scientist Working Group COnsortium of METabolomics Studies	2022 - 2022

# Skills

Languages Italian (native), English (C1, IELTS 7.0), Spanish

(basic)

Programming LanguagesR, Python, MATLAB, CMarkup LanguagesLaTeX, RMarkdown

Software Development git, SLURM, High Performance Scientific Computing